Finding Aid for the Willard Goodwin Collection of William Osler Correspondence Biomed.0295
UCLA Library Special Collections
Willard Goodwin collection of William Osler correspondence
1893-1947
UCLA Library Special Collections
Willard E. Goodwin 1915-1998
Biomed.0295
0.5 Linear Feet (1 box)
The collection is built around two sets of letters: 1. Twenty original letters from William Osler, M.D. to Howard Atwood Kelly, M.D., dated 1897-1917, plus the notes and materials Dr. Goodwin used to write an article for the "Bulletin of the History of Medicine" (20(5): 611-652, Dec. 1946) on the relationship between Osler and Kelly and correspondence pertaining to that article before and after its publication. 2. Transcriptions of many letters from Osler to Henry Barton Jacobs, M.D., dated 1893-1919, and extensive notes made by Dr. Goodwin who probably intended to publish an article based upon this correspondence.
Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9963156263606533
Acquisition Information
Donated to the UCLA Biomedical Library by the family of Willard Goodwin, M.D. in 1999.
Biography
Sir William Osler, 1st Baronet (1849–1919) has been called the Father of Modern Medicine and his influence on medical education and practice is still huge. He was a person of great charm, energy, and wide intellectual interests, who excelled as physician, teacher, bibliophile, and author. Canadian born, he received an M.D. from McGill University, Montreal, and taught there for 10 years. His career continued as Chair of Clinical Medicine at the University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, then first Chief of Staff at Johns Hopkins Hospital and Professor of Medicine at Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, and finally Regius Chair of Medicine at Oxford University. Throughout his life Osler was known to write a large number of notes and letters to his wide circle of friends and acquaintances.
The distinguished American gynecologist Howard Atwood Kelly (1858–1943) received his M.D. from the University of Pennsylvania, where he also taught for a number of years and came to know William Osler. The two were rejoined when Kelly was appointed professor of gynecology and obstetrics at Johns Hopkins University. They made up half of "The Four Doctors" who founded Johns Hopkins Hospital and are depicted in a famous group portrait by John Singer Sargent. The pair also shared an interest in medical history and a strong love of book collecting. Kelly's interest also extended to natural history; he was a herpetologist of some renown.
Henry Barton Jacobs (1858-1939) received his A.B. and M.D. degrees from Harvard University. Within a year of his medical school graduation he moved to Baltimore to become the private physician for Robert Garrett, president of the Baltimore and Ohio Railroad. In 1889 he joined the dispensary service of the newly-opened Johns Hopkins Hospital, under physician-in-chief William Osler. Later he also taught classes in physical diagnosis and therapeutics at the Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine. Dr. Jacobs was especially interested in combating tuberculosis and he took an active role in anti-TB campaigns; for many years he served as secretary of the National Tuberculosis Association. Jacobs was not only a physician serving under Osler's guidance; the two became friends through their shared interest in medical history and collecting of books, and they were close physical neighbors on Franklin Street in Baltimore.
Scope and Content
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1. William Osler letters to Howard A. Kelly, 1897-1947. 10 folders
Series 2. William Osler letters to Henry Barton Jacobs, 1893-1949. 2 folders
Related Material
UCLA BIOMEDICAL LIBRARY HISTORY AND SPECIAL COLLECTIONS FOR THE SCIENCES Manuscript Colletion #181: "Sir William Osler Portrait by Seymour Thomas, and other Osler-Related Papers". Documents about the original portrait and the acquisition and presentation of the replica hung at UCLA, which was obtained through Dr. Elmer Belt's initiative and support. Includes one folder of Osleriana assembled by Elmer Belt and letters to and from him and Willard Goodwin.
Physicians -- |Correspondence, reminiscences, etc.; Jacobs, Henry Barton; Kelly, Howard A. (Howard Atwood); Osler, William, Sir; Goodwin, Willard E. -- Archives
- William Osler letters to Howard A. Kelly, 1897-1947; Series 1.; 10 folders
  Scope and Contents note
  Original letters; research materials and notes for Goodwin article; documents regarding publication of the article, and correspondence commenting on it
  - Letters from Dr. William Osler to Dr. Howard A. Kelly, 1897-1917 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Twenty short letters or notes, mostly handwritten, a few typed, addressed to "Dear Kelly" or "Dear Howard A."
    General note
    the group of letters was a gift to Dr. Goodwin from his uncle, Dr. Elmer Belt
  - "William Osler and Howard A. Kelly, 'Physicians, Medical Historians, Friends,' as revealed by nineteen letters from Osler to Kelly", by Willard E. Goodwin. In: "Bulletin of the History of Medicine", 20(no. 5): 611-652, Dec. 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    One whole journal issue, two reprints; list of people receiving reprints from Dr. Goodwin
  - Draft of article text, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Original copy with author's corrections; carbon copy with some corrections and annotations by W. W. Francis
  - Dr. Goodwin's working notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Photocopies of original letters with typed transcriptions of hand-written ones; Dr. Goodwin's notes and annotations
  - Letters to Goodwin re. his Osler-Kelly article, 1946-1965 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Comments and appreciations for the article, all including some Osler/Kelly anecdotes or reminiscences; also a note from Seymour Thomas commenting on his painting of the Osler portrait
  - Additional letters re. the Osler-Kelly article, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Notes of appreciation for reprints of the article, or requests for a copy
  - Correspondence re. publication of the Osler-Kelly article, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Letters from Elmer Belt, W. W. Francis, and the publisher
  - William Osler's "chloroform" speech, 1946-1965 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Letters and reprints concerning remarks made by Osler in his farewell address at Johns Hopkins University
  - William Osler's "chloroform" speech, 1946-1965 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Reprints of articles on Osler, 1925-1949 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Includes many reprints from the Osler centenary issue of "Archives of Internal Medicine", v. 84, July 1949
  - Photographs of Osler, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Snapshots at various ages in various locations; photograph of a cartoon referring to the "chloroform" speech
- William Osler letters to Henry Barton Jacobs, 1893-1949; Series 2.; 2 folders
  Transcriptions and excerpts from the letters; notes by Dr. Goodwin; introduction to a speech by Dr. Goodwin based on the content of the letters
  - William Osler letters to Henry Barton Jacobs, 1893-1910; folder 1 or 2 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Typed transcriptions of ca. forty letters from Osler to Jacobs, addressed to "Dear Jacobs". Notes by Goodwin on content and context of many of the letters
    there are two partial sets of notes and transcriptions, typed on different paper and typewriters
  - William Osler letters to Henry Barton Jacobs, 1911-1919; folder 2 of 2 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Ca. forty more letters with Goodwin notes